Guide to the György Kepes papers M1796
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 6. Notes and research files
  - 6.1. Notes and research: general
    - Notes on Art and Scale (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Handwritten notes and corrected typed material mostly relating to topics of scale in art.
    - Light and Color Modulation - Notes and Typescripts (Box 17, Folder 2)
      Handwritten notes and corrected typed materials on light and color.
    - Art - Notes and Typed Material (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Consists of quotations and other material from other artists and theorists.
    - Notes and Printed Material (Box 17, Folder 7)
      Corrected material from Kepes's work on light, color, and the city. Much of the printed material is redundant with earlier documents, but the written portions appear to be different.
    - Typescript about relation of art to life (Box 17, Folder 10)
      19 page manuscript, unsigned, undated.
    - Notes and Drawings (Box 17, Folder 13)
      Undated notes and drawings on light, color, perception, and sound.
    - Printed Material 1947, 1972, 1973, 1985, undated (Box 17, Folder 14)
      Heavily corrected typescripts on various subjects, including urbanism, such as The Baltimore Project and projects in and around Boston. Bulk undated.
    - Notes and Typescripts (Box 17, Folder 17)
      Various notes and typescripts primarily about light and photography.
    - Notes and Printed Material (Box 25, Folder 1)
      Handwritten notes by Kepes and printed material by Albert Camus, Edward T. Hall, and others.
    - Notes and Printed Material 1978, undated (Box 25, Folder 6)
      Printed material interspersed with hand-written notes. Original folder was labeled "European Friends."
    - Notes and Printed Material 1965 and undated (Box 25, Folder 10)
      Mostly undated. Hand-written notes and copies of printed material, including quotations from famous authors, including Charles Dickens and Henry David Thoreau.
    - Vision, 1978-1987 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      Correspondence and other material relating to exhibitions as well as light and perception. Some material in Hungarian.
    - Notes and printed material 1969, undated (Box 26, Folder 10)
      Subjects include the Light Tower, movement, and science and art.
    - Photocopies (Box 27, Folder 12)
      Photocopies of several unsigned publications. Topic include "The Inclined Galactic Light Pond Bamiyan, Afghanistan", "The Utopic Vessel", and others. Presumably by Kepes. Poetry.
    - Printed Material, 1954, 1965 (Box 28, Folder 7)
      Carbons of typescripts - "Light and Color" from 1965 and "Topics for Seminar Discussion" from 1954. Seminar is on the city and urban life.
    - Printed material (Box 28, Folder 14)
      Much of this material consists of sheets of paper taken out of context from larger works. Also includes writings by Kepes, quotes from artists such as Van Gogh, and a short essay by Carl Nesjar called Fountains for All Seasons. Some material in German.
    - Manuscript on Sight (Box 28, Folder 24)
      Unsigned article on sight. On MIT stationery, presumably by Kepes.
    - Visual Forms - Structural Forms, 1948 (Box 28, Folder 28)
      Manuscript of a text by Kepes.
    - Art and Ecological Consciousness (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Notes and Printed Material 1982-1985, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
      Bulk undated. Much of it is random out-of-context pages. Some meeting agendas for various organizations, other materials.
    - Printed Material, mostly undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
      Mostly out-of-context pages with a few short complete pieces by Kepes and others.
    - Essay on Interdependence (Box 29, Folder 17)
      Typescript with hand-written contracts of an untitled essay by Kepes about modernity and human interdependence.
    - History of human thought (Box 29, Folder 20)
      Photostat of a typed essay by Kepes about human history and the hope of transforming the world.
    - Printed Material and notes 1971, undated (Box 30, Folder 11)
      Printed pages, biographies of Kepes, writings by Kepes, press release, business card - mostly seems unrelated, but all found together originally.
    - Light Materials, 1964 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - Typescript, untitled, 1969 (Box 32, Folder 8)
      Typescript of a manuscript with hand-written corrections. Seems to be on "individual artistic imagination."
    - Printed Material 1965, 1978, undated (Box 33, Folder 24)
      Bulk undated. Miscellaneous printed material by Kepes and others.
    - Typescript on Perception (Box 34, Folder 1)
      Two copies of a manuscript of a text on perception. Presumably by Kepes.
    - Environment Essays, Re-edited and re-typed, 1969-1970 (Box 38, Folder 9)
      Hand-corrected typescripts.
    - Bibliography, 1959-1965 (Box 39, Folder 2)
      Lists of works and other bibliographic material.
    - Completed Manuscripts (Box 78, Folders 1-2)
      G. Kepes manuscripts including but not limited to essays, book chapters, and speeches.
    - Manuscripts (Box 80, Folders 1-4, Box 79, Folders 2-5)
      G. Kepes manuscripts including but not limited to essays, book chapters, speeches, professional correspondence and other miscellaneous notes.
    - Academic Notes (Box 81, Folders 4-5)
      Miscellaneous notes and correspondence.
    - Manuscripts (Box 82, Folders 2-6)
    - Light Start, 1937, 1939 (Box 50, Folder 2)
      Drawings and notes for Light Start. Ink on Paper. Also two letters from Moholy-Nagy and others about the intention to start a school of design in Chicago.
    - Kepes, 1936-2002 (Box 50, Folder 9)
      Correspondence, clippings, drawings. Originally in folder together.
    - Notes (Box 58, Folder 1)
      Two pages of handwritten notes. List of photocopies to be made. Appears to be a list of what appears in the rest of the box.
    - Kepes (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - Aesthetics of Everyday Life (Box 58, Folder 7)
    - Contents of an Un-marked File (Box 58, Folder 8)
      Photocopy of a typescript. Title comes from a sticky note affixed to the first page.
    - Shaping of the Exhibition, The (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - Contents of File, Light on a New Scale Final Copy, 1974-02-25 (Box 58, Folder 13)
      Photocopies. Title comes from a sticky-note.
    - Misc. reports, papers and reprints (Box 105, Folder 1, Box 104, Folder 5)
      Contains reports, reprints, and science and philosophy magazines. Includes inscribed reprints from Rudolf Arnheim, Roman Jakobson, and others, a booklet printing an S.I. Hayakawa lecture, and material from the American Academy of Arts & Sciences.
    - Handwritten notes (Box 105, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous typed notes (Box 105, Folder 16)
    - Scientists and Engineers for McCarthy ad reprint, 1967 (Box 105, Folder 23)
    - unidentified mock-up of geometric figures (Box 105, Folder 25)
    - unidentified diagram (Box 105, Folder 26)
    - unidentified diagram (Box 105, Folder 27)
    - misc. images, clipped and photocopied (Box 105, Folder 28)
  - 6.2. Notes and research: urban studies, architecture, noise pollution, etc.
    - Urban Form: Seminar typescripts, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Two typescripts for seminars on urban form; one titled "URBAN FORM: Seminar 12/10/54 Interview with John Cage, composer, James T. Farrell, writer, and Anrdreas Feininger, photographer," second titled "URBAN FORM SEMINAR: 10/29/54," recording discussion between Kepes, Rudolf Arnheim, Kevin Lynch, Jerome Bruner, Tagiuri, Adams, Kelly, Rodwin.
    - Paul Earls, Notes: Anechoic Acoustical Events (Box 8, Folder 7)
      Typescript by Paul Earls with Mem-O-Gram addressed to Prof. Kepes.
    - Listening Incorporated (Box 8, Folder 6)
      Promotional material from Listening Incorporated on auditory technology.
    - Noise and miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Typescript on noise with miscellaneous manuscript on "the basic task of the contemporary artist" and one page relating to light.
    - Boston noise ordinance (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Auditory notes (Box 8, Folder 2)
      1 page handwritten notes on noise.
    - Clippings on noise (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Copies and original press articles dealing with noise and noise pollution.
    - Form of the city notes 1, 1954-1958 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Correspondence from Kevin Lynch and G. Kepes to Charles B. Fahs, Director, Division of Humanities, The Rockefeller Foundation, re: "The Perceptual Form of the City." Partial typescript titled "Dr. David H. Hubel." Typed notes tiled "THE FORM OF CITY STUDY." Typescript titled "THE PERCEPTUAL FORM OF THE CITY GENERAL REPORT AND PLAN FOR FUTURE STUDIES -- May 17, 1955." Typescript titled "A FRAMEWORK FOR THE FORM OF CITY STUDY AND SOME TOPICS FOR STUDY." Typescript titled "NOTES ON DISCUSSION BETWEEN L.A. AND J.R.M AND G.K., K.L. AND J.R.MM. ON OR ABOUT MARCH 20, 1958." Typed proposal dated March 4, 1954 and titled "Proposed Study: THE PERCEPTUAL FORM OF THE CITY." Memo from Dave Crane to G. Kepes and associated typed notes for Crane lecture given at Harvard Graduate School of Design 1/6/56. Typed bibliography titled "Recomended References on the Form of the City."
    - Form of the city notes 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Handwritten notes titled "intrinsic symbol," "space symbols," "city," and miscellaneous notes with drawings and sketches.
    - Urban environment notes, 1968-1971 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Handwritten notes on "homeostasis," "envrionmental art," and other topics; typescripts, mostly untitled, including 4 undated, 2 typescripts dated 2/3/69, 1 typescript dated 1/14/69, 1 typescript dated 11/19/68, 1 typescript dated both 1/20/69 and 4/15/71, typescript with crossed-out title "The Crisis of the City: Symbolic Forms," typescript dated both 11/20/68 and 9/23/70, and some miscellaneous manuscript pages. Typescripts heavily annotated.
    - Architecture and Urban Planning Sketches and Notes 1974, undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
      Drawings, sketches, notes.
    - Architecture and Cities - Notes and Typed Material, 1960s (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Urban Form notes and printed material 1954, 1984, 1966, bulk undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
      Notes and printed material, both generally about the urban condition and more specifically about Boston and its Back Bay neighborhood.
    - Urbanism Publications, 1970, 1972 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      Published material on Highway Sculpture and Spielstrasse - some in German.
    - Urban Projects Correspondence, Photographs and Printed Material, 1954-1978 (Box 27, Folder 9)
      Includes photographs of art works, proposals and other correspondence for Boston Harbor and Times Square projects, as well as more general material about urban issues.
    - Arnold Berleant. Aesthetic Paradigms For an Urban Ecology, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 23)
      Manuscript of a paper written by Arnold Berleant of Long Island University. Article was published in the journal Diogenes in Fall 1978.
    - Eduardo Terrazas and Raimundo Cuervo. The Unbuilding Industry, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 23)
      Pamphlet by Eduardo Terrazas and Raimundo Cuervo for HABITAT FORUM, a UN conference on May 31-June 11, 1976.
    - John G. Papaioannou. Sensory Aspects: A Tentative List of Topics and Problems Relating Man to His Settlements, 1968 (Box 30, Folder 7)
      Manuscript of an article by John G. Papaioannou from the Athens Technological Organization's 1968 Athens Ekistics Month.
    - Architectural Lettering Yale Symposium (Box 38, Folder 10)
      Hand-corrected typescript.
    - Public Art and Architecture 1974, undated (Box 28, Folder 33)
      Various materials for architecture and public art projects, including for La Defense in Paris, the Charles River, and public space.
- Series 7: Notes, articles, correspondence, etc.
  Original processing for this collection retained original order, even when folders contained an assortment of apparently unrelated clippings, notes, correspondence, and published items. This series contains most of these folders (mostly named Assorted Material, Miscellaneous Material, or Printed Material), some of which contain items relevant to other series. See also Kepes research files.
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 17, Folders 5-6, Folder 12)
    Several sheets of printed material. Some of it is quotes from Leon Trotsky. Undated material appears to be excerpts from Kepes' various writings on art, color, and urbanism. Dated item is a press release for the 1986 MIT SKY ART Conference.
  - Printed Material 1940 and undated (Box 25, Folder 15)
    Contains three documents: a program for a dance concert, a list of participants in an unnamed conference, and a brief biography of Kepes.
  - Miscellaneous Material 1973, undated (Box 25, Folder 18)
    Business card for Lengyel Lajos, Poem by Virginia Baylor, and printed magazine-style images of various churches.
  - Printed Material 1972, undated (Box 26, Folder 3)
    Miscellaneous printed material, some hand-corrected, on various subjects. Also includes letter from Ken Halpern to Kepes on March 1, 1972.
  - Printed Material and photographs 1949, 1962, undated (Box 26, Folder 14)
    Printed material, including exhibition publicity, and photographs of works by Masuyaki Nagare and an unknown artist.
  - Printed Material in German (Box 27, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of pages 2 to 38 of an unidentified document written in German.
  - Arts Organizations, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 22)
    Nomination materials and correspondence related to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the National Academy of Design, the National Institute of Arts and Letters, and the American Society for Aesthetics.
  - Miscellaneous Material 2002, undated (Box 27, Folder 33)
    Item from 2002 is a printed street map of a portion of London. Also contains two maps of Welfleet, MA, a postcard from the Mexican National Anthropological Museum, and a card from the Bauhaus Archive in Berlin with Kepes' name written on it. Material all found adjacent in original grouping. Also contains two out-of-context printed pages.
  - Miscellaneous, 1984, 1994 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    American Academy of Arts and Sciences Election letter, and program for the 1984 memorial service for Kevin Lynch. Memorial service program has handwritten notes by Kepes on the back.
  - Printed material and notes (Box 28, Folder 15)
    Primarily out-of-context printed material. Also includes a few hand-written notes. All of this material was originally in an untitled folder together.
  - Printed material and notes 1971, undated (Box 28, Folder 17)
    Bulk of the material is out-of-context printed matter. One sheet of handwritten notes.
  - Printed material and clippings (Box 28, Folder 22)
    Mostly out-of-context, difficult-to-decipher material. Some in German and Hungarian.
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material (Box 28, Folder 25)
  - Event Programs, 1985 (Box 28, Folder 29)
    Programs for awards by the American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters and the George Washington Awards.
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material (Box 28, Folder 36)
    Includes short writings, probably by Kepes, as well as quotes from others. No apparent order.
  - Printed Material and notes 1985, undated (Box 29, Folder 2)
    Bulk undated. Includes event programs, clippings, miscellaneous printed material, and other unrelated material.
  - Printed Material and Correspondence 1980s, undated (Box 29, Folder 10)
    Mostly out-of-context partial printed documents. Includes a small amount of correspondence between Kepes and Faith Atlass. Also includes miscellaneous other materials.
  - Printed material and notes, undated (Box 29, Folder 15)
  - Printed Material, Correspondence, and Clippings, 1975-1985 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Printed Material, 1960s-1970s, undated (Box 30, Folder 15)
    Bulk undated. Mostly out-of-context material. Some material concerns the Center for Advanced Visual Studies. Press releases.
  - Printed material, 1970s (Box 30, Folder 26)
    Printed material, clippings, two photographs, and correspondence. All unrelated, much of it is random printed pages. One of the photographs is of the Harvard Square stained glass piece.
  - Printed Material (Box 30, Folder 29)
  - Assorted material (Box 31, Folder 2)
    A few items are dated. Unrelated material, including press releases, handwritten notes, random printed material, and publicity material.
  - Assorted material, 1970s (Box 31, Folder 5)
    Much of it is undated. Much of the material is random out-of-context printed material. Also includes unlabeled photographs, clippings, and miscellaneous correspondence.
  - Cambridge Art Association (CAA) - Kerlan Library Collection, Other Information, 1980-1981 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Assorted Material 1985, undated (Box 31, Folder 10)
    Mostly printed material and correspondence. Bulk undated. Some material involves the Upper and Lower Falls Project.
  - Assorted Material 1973, undated (Box 31, Folder 11)
    Includes stamps, a newspaper clipping, and two interviews. One has various avant garde figures including John Cage.
  - Printed Material and clippings 1980s, undated (Box 31, Folder 12)
  - Printed material and notes (Box 31, Folder 13)
  - Assorted Material, 1980-1982 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    Correspondence, loan agreements, a contract with the MBTA and clippings.
  - Printed material (Box 31, Folder 15)
    Contains a manuscript of an article by "Jackson" entitled "The City and the Garden."
  - Assorted Material, 1972-1982 (Box 31, Folder 17)
    Mostly assorted printed material. Some correspondence and clippings. One photo.
  - Assorted material 1972, undated (Box 31, Folder 18)
    Correspondence, printed material, one photo of the moon.
  - Printed Material and clippings 1973, undated (Box 31, Folder 21)
  - Assorted Material (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material, 1966-1969 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Assorted Material 1965-1978, undated (Box 33, Folder 25)
    Bulk undated. Out-of-context printed material, clippings, publicity materials, and a small amount of correspondence.
  - Assorted Materials 1973-1987, undated (Box 34, Folders 2-3)
  - Printed material (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Assorted Materials, 1977-1989, undated (Box 34, Folder 5)
    Bulk undated. Mostly clippings and exhibition publicity materials. Small amount of correspondence and out-of-context printed material.
  - Press Materials, 1973-1994 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    Press releases and publicity materials. Contains a photographic print of various representations of the letter E.
  - Assorted Material, 1970-1996 (Box 34, Folder 11)
    Bulk printed material. Large amount of corresondence, and a few clippings. Items were interspersed in such a way as to preclude further breakdown into categories.
  - Assorted Material 1987, undated (Box 34, Folder 13)
    One letter and one page of out-of-context printed material. The letter is from James Melchert at the American Academy in Rome.
  - Assorted Material 1977-1987, undated (Box 34, Folder 14)
    Bulk undated. Much out-of-context printed material. Correspondence, clippings, a few drawings, one photograph.
  - Assorted Material, 1966-1982 (Box 34, Folder 17)
    Correspondence, clippings, and printed material.
  - Printed Material 1982-1994, undated (Box 35, Folder 11)
    Bulk undated. Clippings, publicity materials, legal materials.
  - Printed Material 1977, undated (Box 35, Folder 14)
    Two news clippings and a legal document.
  - Assorted Material 1994, undated (Box 35, Folder 16)
    Bulk undated. Includes correspondence, drawing, and out-of-context printed material.
  - Assorted Material 1986, 1987, undated (Box 36, Folder 2)
    Bulk undated. Bulk drawings. Some correspondence and printed material.
  - Assorted Material, 1978-1979 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    Contains photographs and correspondence.
  - Publications, 1947-1965 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material (Box 38, Folder 13)
    Carbons of random printed material.
  - Sao Paulo Biennale, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 8)
    Printed material about the United States contribution to the 1969 Sao Paulo Biennale.
  - Interdependence, 1959, 1968 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    Publications and a press release.
  - GK: Math, 1964-1969 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    Clippings and publications.
  - Assorted Material, 1947-1978 (Box 48, Folder 4)
    Mostly clippings, as well as a press release and some publicity materials. Originally in unlabeled folder together.
  - Miscellaneous Loose Items, 1964-1972 (Box 58, Folders 17-18)
- Series 8. Articles & clippings
  - Articles and clippings on light technology (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Articles and clippings from Science, IEEE Spectrum, National Geographic, Internaiontal Science and Technology, New York Times, and elsewhere; includes promotional material from Ferrofluidics Corporation.
  - Articles and clippings on art and light technology (Box 4, Folder 16)
    From Arts Magazine, Art News, Studio International, Art International, and elsewhere.
  - Articles and clippings on light technology (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Mostly technical and scientific but includes some articles on art.
  - Clippings on Kepes paintings (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Undated clippings from Italian art publication with reproductions of Kepes's paintings.
  - Clippings 1976-1977, 1982, undated (Box 27, Folder 19)
    Four clippings - one is in Hungarian. One in English is from the New York Times Book Review, and is undated. It is a review of several of Kepes' books by Roger Jellinek. Two are exhibition reviews.
  - Clippings 1983, 1992, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
    In Hungarian and English.
  - Clippings, 1971-1974 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    Newspaper clippings from the Boston Globe and Christian Science Monitor about Kepes.
  - Clippings 1964 and undated (Box 28, Folder 18)
    Two clippings - one on Kepes' Harvard Square stained glass wall and one on his Times Square project.
  - Clippings (Box 28, Folder 26)
    One clipping is on Yves Klein by Larry Rivers.
  - Clippings, 1970, 1984, 1999 (Box 28, Folder 31)
    Clippings about art matters, including Rockne Krebs, Bill Parker, and Peter Scott.
  - Clippings, 1971-1976 (Box 28, Folder 34)
    Various clippings from the 1970s from newspapers and magazines.
  - Clippings 1984 and undated (Box 28, Folder 37)
  - Clippings, 1947-1985 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    Bulk 1980s. Clippings on various art-related subjects.
  - Clippings and Printed Materials, 1974 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    Clippings in German and English, plus Abt Associates annual report and an unknown photo.
  - Graphical Clippings (Box 30, Folder 8)
    Clippings of printed reproductions of art works.
  - Clippings 1960-1962, undated (Box 30, Folder 14)
    Some in German.
  - Clippings, 1947-1974 (Box 30, Folder 19)
  - Clippings and printed material 1974, undated (Box 31, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, 1943-1971 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1952-1973 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1954-1985 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Clipping From article entitled "Pictures that Reveal Nature --Or Do They? By Gene Throton." (Box 42, Folder 4)
    Possibly from New York Times.
  - Clippings, 1965-1972 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1961-1973 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1966-1971 (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1966-1989 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1965-1990 (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1965-1985 (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - Clipping from Chicago Magazine, 1972-11-12 (Box 42, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1962-1977, undated (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles (Box 81, Folders 1-3)
    Articles and clippings from Science Journal, IEEE Spectrum, National Geographic, International Science and Technology, New York Times, and others. Some correspondence and notes.
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles (Box 82, Folder 1)
    Newspaper articles and art pamphlets.
  - Clippings (Box 55, Folder 2)
    Assorted clippings referencing work by Kepes.
- Series 9. Kepes in magazines [chronological]